Today's דף daf is דף מ"ח. daf Mem-Chet. We start at the
bottom of מ"ז עמוד ב', Mem-Zayin Amud-Beis, right after the משנה. mishna.
We turn to a new פרק. perek. Last פרק perek was about
leaving stuff on the fire, but it got into nice discussions about
בישול bishul and then a major discussion about מוקצה. muktzah. We return
now to putting stuff on the fire before שבת, Shabbat, but now,
rather than putting it on the fire so it continues to cook,
it's done cooking and you want to insulate it so that it
retains the heat. And this is called הטמנה, hatmanah, טומנים, tomnim, which
can mean like to bury or the a good word that Michael
suggested yesterday was insulate. So normally what they would do, the best
way to insulate things and to keep the heat would be you
store it in the hot ashes. Of course then, just like the
concern about leaving something on an open flame, is a concern that
you might come to stir them up in order to, you know,
reignite them or to get it to be hotter. So therefore, the
Rabbis said because of that model of insulating in hot ashes, you
are not allowed to הטמין hatmin in anything you're not allowed to
insulate even ערב שבת Erev Shabbat in anything that adds heat, like
hot ashes. Even if it's something that is unrelated to fire. And
the משנה mishna had a whole list of things that added heat.
Primarily, actually, the scientists here can tell us, I was told that
basically what types of things actually create heat other than fire? That
these are all organic matters and as they're decomposing, they're releasing their
heat. And that's a lot of what is going on here about
the things that add heat. So you cannot store in things that
add heat before שבת, Shabbat, and the משנה mishna went into a
whole list of what types of materials will add the heat. Yes,
Dr. Charlie.
So dung will add will add heat because it's released as it
right. But sand?
If it's hot sand.
Only if it's hot, maybe maybe it has retained heat. Right. So
I don't know, I don't know. Let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו, Ibayu lehu, so the גמרא Gemara asks,
גפת, gefet, which was one of the first things mentioned you cannot
use, I mistranslated it yesterday as the sort of as the פסולת
psolet like the leftover of the grapes. Actually that's this is the
leftover from olives. So it's like olive you know, the olive branches
or olive wood or the olive twigs. Okay, so that's גפת. של
זיתים gefet shel zeitim תנן, is it talking about olives? אבל דשומשמין
שפיר דמי, Aval deshumshumin shapir dami, but of sesame it's fine. I've
never actually seen a what is it, a sesame tree? Where do
you get sesames from? Is it a plant? So anyway, I have
no idea what this
is. But anyway, alright. But that type of remnant that you get
when you sort from sesames, that's okay. או דלמא דשומשמין תנן, O
dilma deshumshumin tnan,
or maybe we're talking even sesames, וכל שכן דזיתים, vechol shekein dezeitim,
certainly of olives. They certainly knew the מציאותא, metziuta, the reality of
what they were discussing and for they took it for granted that
the stuff from olives releases more heat than the stuff from sesames.
So the question is, you know, is even the stuff of sesames
a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, Ta shma, come
hear, דאמר רב זירא משום חד דבי רבי ינאי, d'amar Rav Zeira
mishum chad debei Rabbi Yannai, that Rav Zeira said in the name
of one person from the house of Rabbi Yannai: קופה שטמן בה,
Kupa shetaman ba,
if you actually have a you've insulated your pot in a box.
Let's say you've got your box, it's filled with whatever, wool or
something, some type of a thing that it's allowed to be filled
with, that's not going to add heat, that'll just retain heat. So
you've got your pot in a box, the box is filled with,
I don't know, you know, those Styrofoam peanuts or something. It's done
with something that'll help, a towel. It was done with filled with
stuff that'll retain heat but not add heat. Don't put that on
top of a box filled with this גפת gefet. של זיתים because
then it adds heat. And this, by the way, is extremely important
because basically ערב שבת Erev Shabbat I want to put my stuff
on my בלעך. blech. Okay, I want to wrap it in a
towel. Well, a towel only retains heat, doesn't add heat, no problem.
But actually, no. I'm putting it on the בלעך blech underneath which
is adding the heat and the towel on top which is retaining
the heat, but combined, that's a whole apparatus that is adding heat,
right? So we'll discuss why I'm allowed to do that or under
what circumstances in a minute. But that's the scenario here. You've got
it wrapped in a towel in a box, that's fine. But now
you want to put it on top of a box of these
גפת gefet which is going to add heat, it's like the בלעך
blech underneath. So that's like a case of adding heat, being insulating
it in things that add heat, not just that retain heat. So
let's take a look. קופה שטמן בה אסור להניחה על גפת של
זיתים. Kupa shetaman ba assur lehaniach al gefet shel zeitim. So you're
not allowed to put this box with the pot in it on
top of the גפת, gefet, the thank you, the twigs of olives.
שמע מינה של זיתים תנן, Shema mina shel zeitim tnan, so you
see, it's explicit. It says olives. So presumably it wouldn't have said
olives if it were including even the lesser example of the sesames.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. לעולם אימא לך הטמנה דשומשמין נמי
אסור, Le'olam eima lach hatmanah deshumshumin nami assur, really I'll tell you
that when it comes to הטמנה, hatmanah, even the sesames is a
problem, they add heat. נמי אסור. Nami assur. ועינין אסוקי הבלא דזיתים
מסקי הבלא דשומשמין לא מסקי הבלא. Ve'inyan asukei havla dezeitim maski havla
deshumshumin lo maski havla. However, here's the difference. The difference is is
that if it were surrounded by the sesame twigs, that would be
a problem, they would add heat. But it's not. It's surrounded by
towels in a box. box, and it's on top of a box
of sesame twigs. So there, it's not enough that the thing adds
heat. For that to be a problem, it have to make heat
rise up. It has to like, right, it's not just enough that
a little heat dissipates all around, so there, it's only a problem
of the olives. The olive twigs will, more heat will rise up
and being on the bottom is a problem, but
and a sesame's not, but surrounding it even sesame's a problem. Okay,
fine. Now let's take a break though for a minute, there's a
very important תוספות Tosafos that discusses how do we do what we
do? Because what do we do? We go ahead and we, let's
start with this. We first of all put our stuff on a
בלעך blech before שבת. Shabbos. Now, we just learned the whole משנה
Mishna about שהיה, Shehiya, but if you can't put it or surround
it, if you get insulated in something that adds heat, maybe all
the earlier cases we're talking about that you swept it out or
you put so much ashes on it or whatever that no heat
is being added. As soon as we're dealing with a reality, with
a case where heat is added, how is that not the case
in the משנה Mishna about insulating in something that adds heat? So
this is a very key problem because תוספות Tosafos is the first
to address it. What is the difference between הטמנה Hatmana and שהיה?
Shehiya? Very key question. And in תוספות's Tosafos time what they used
to do is take a pot and actually, now what you might
have wanted to think is, well let's say if it's flat like
a בלעך, blech, that's not actually insulating, it's just underneath. Okay, but
in תוספות's Tosafos time what they would do is they would actually
insert a pot into hot ashes at the bottom, and the hot
ashes would actually be around, not the whole height of the pot,
but be it would be inserted a little bit. So that's a
little sense of insulating. So even though it's הטמנה, Hatmana, even though
it's גרוף וקטום, Garuf veKatuman, swept out, it's still a problem of
insulating. Why should that not be an issue? So if you take
a look at תוספות דזיתין, Tosafos d'zaysin, תוספות Tosafos says like this.
Well let's start from the beginning. מכאן יש לאסור להניח גחלים תחת
הקדרה. mikan yesh le'esor lehani'ach gechalim tachas hakedera. From here you should
infer if you can't have the olive stuff underneath that raises heat,
you should infer that you cannot have coals under the pot. אפילו
יתן עליהם אפר אין להטמין קדרה עליהם, afillu yiten aleihem efer ein
lehatmin kedera aleihem, even if they have the ashes on it, how
can you put the pot on top of it? שהרי גחלים מעלים
הבל למעלה, sheharei gechalim ma'alim hevel lemala, because they raise heat above.
Isn't that this case of insulating? כמו גפת של זיתים. kemo gefes
shel zaysim. ויש תמה, ve'yesh teima, then you could be astounded. היכא
אנו מטמינים על כירה שלנו, heicha anu matminim al kira shelanu,
how do we do what we do, which is we put it
into the ovens
שקורין אסטרווא shekorin astrova דאף על פי שגורפין אותו הוא מוסיף הבל
כמי גפת של זיתים. de'af al pi shegorfin oso hu mosif hevel
kemo gefes shel zaysim. Our way we put stuff on the stove
top or in the oven ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you put it
in the oven, you turn off the oven, you can do that,
right? So that's adding heat. How is that allowed? Okay, and this
רי Ri is one of the most important ריס Ris in the
laws of הטמנה. Hatmana. ואומר רי. ve'omer Ri. Now by the way,
well I will first tell you תוספות Tosafos there's a second answer,
which is not relevant for us, but is important
because would limit the allowances of הטמנה. Hatmana. תוספות Tosafos says, well
maybe the difference is, תוספות Tosafos says in his case the heat
is dissipating, whereas in the case and that's maybe not considered הטמנה
במוסיף הבל. Hatmana b'mosif hevel. So true it's a hot oven, but
the heat is only going in one direction, going down, going out.
In the case of the משנה, Mishna, if we're dealing with as
I said organic matter that is decomposing, it's actually creating new heat.
It's not just losing its stored heat. Okay, now if you made
that distinction we'd be in trouble because that would mean anytime that
you're adding that you're not just dissipating heat but actually creating new
heat, it's הטמנה, Hatmana, we couldn't keep our stuff on the stove
top on שבת. Shabbos. And you'd have to explain the entire previous
פרק Perek that all the heat was actually dissipating and that's what
made it okay, but if new heat is being created, right, that's
a problem. So thankfully that is not the answer that תוספות Tosafos
focuses on. He focuses on the רי's Ri answer, which is the
biggest difference, which is the big line between הטמנה Hatmana and שהיה.
Shehiya. And here's what the רי Ri says. ואומר רי שיש ליתן
טעם לקיים המנהג דלגבי גפת איכא למיחש שמא יטמין כולה בתוכה אבל
בכירה שלנו לא שייך למיחש להכי. ve'omer Ri she'yesh liten ta'am lekayem
haminhag de'legabei gefes ika lemeichash shema yatmin kula besocha aval be'kira shelanu
lo shayach lemeichash lehachi. Okay, so
he says, well it's here in our case it's not possible to
fully immerse it. So only if it's possible to fully submerse it,
that would be an issue, but if it can't be fully submersed,
it's not a problem. And then he goes on. According to that
though maybe you can't keep it in an oven, inside of the
oven it's fully surrounded. ועוד יש ליתן טעם שעושים חפירה גדולה ועושים
בה בנין לבנים סביב מכל צד ומלמטה ומניחין שם הקדרה וגורפין אותה
ומטמינים בה את הקדרה. ve'od yesh liten ta'am she'osim chafira gedola ve'osim
ba binyan levenim saviv mikol tzad umilmata u'manichin sham hakedera ve'gorfin osa
u'matminim ba es hakedera.
Okay, so anyway he has another example where similarly where it could
maybe be fully submersed, it's not but it could be. And then
he says,
where were we? ולא דמי להטמנה בדבר המוסיף הבל דלא אסרו אלא
כשמטמינו בדביק סביב הקדרה דומיא דרמץ ve'lo dami l'hatmana b'davar hamosif hevel
de'lo asru ela k'sh'matminu b'davik saviv hakedera dumya d'remetz אבל תנור או
חפירה שיש אויר בין הדפנות להקדרה אין לאסור יותר משאר שעה אף
על פי שכל הקדרה בתוך התנור. aval tanur o chafira she'yesh avir
bein hadafanos lakedera ein le'esor yoser mish'ar sha'ah af al pi shekol
hakedera besoch hatanur.
And that's like one of the most important תוספותים Tosafoses about this
whole discussion, which is if your pot can be fully in the
oven, it's not considered הטמנה בדבר המוסיף הבל Hatmana b'davar hamosif hevel
because there's air space between the pot and the surrounding
oven. Not like here we're talking about an insulating material that is
totally touching it on all sides. Okay, so if you're going to
put, and that is the big difference. The big question about the
crock pot is, how many sides do you mean by all sides?
Do we include the top as well? So some people say the
crock pot is הטמנה hatmana because it literally touches on all sides.
Okay, but the cover isn't touched, so some people have the hotpot
as הטמנה, hatmana, some people say the hotpot is not הטמנה. hatmana.
If you're putting a towel over, right, so a towel only keeps
the heat, it doesn't add the heat, but let's say you have
your בלעך blech and a towel on top, okay? Anybody do that?
בלעך blech with a towel on top? Yes. Okay, so that's exactly
this case in the גמרא. Gemara. You have the heat being added,
you know, plus it's being kept. How is that okay? So if
the towel does not surround it on all sides, basically you make
sort of like a tent with the towel, you know, it stretches
from like the back of the stove top towards like the lower
part of the stove, whatever, but it's not sort of, you know,
even if it sort of falls, right, even if it falls, it
sort of falls at an angle, so the, you know, the food
is here and the towel is coming down like that. If you
actually, no, but if you actually compressed it, that would be a
הטמנה. hatmana. So this תוספות Tosafot makes הטמנה hatmana a very small
category and makes almost everything we do into a case of שהייה,
shehiya, which gives us a lot more latitude because once you address
the בלעך blech problem and so on, you're okay even though heat
is being
added. What? Maybe in like, you know, the next answer of תוספות
Tosafot gives a much a different answer, but in practice, this is
totally the answer that's adopted for what defines as הטמנה. hatmana.
Yes. Why would the box be a problem underneath?
Because there it's surrounded by insulating material. The pot is surrounded by
let's say a towel, so that's הטמנה, hatmana, and you add to
הטמנה hatmana heat, then it's considered הטמנה במוסיף הבל. hatmana bimosif hevel.
So if you left, if the top of it was just in
the box without packed with towels, you'd be okay. That's like leaving
something on the בלעך. blech. Okay? So that is critical תוספות Tosafot
for practical aspects of הטמנה. hatmana. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like
this. רבה ורבי זירא איקלעו לבי ריש גלותא. Rabba verabi Zeira iklu
levei Reish Galuta. Second line from the top. רבה ורבי זירא Rabba
verabi Zeira came to the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta
where often in the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta there
are people not being, I mean he has a lot of servants
and he was, like I said, the political Jewish head, but not
necessarily the frummest guy around. So sometimes there are practices going around
that are
inappropriate. חזיוה לההוא עבדא, Chazyuha lehahu avda, they saw a certain servant,
דאנח כוזא דמיא אפומא דקומקומא, daanach kuza demaya apuma dekumkuma,
that he put a flask of water on the mouth, like on
the top of
a kettle, a hot water, you know, a pot that had hot
water in it.
נזייה רבה, Nazyei Rabba, so Rabba yelled at him. So אמר ליה
רבי זירא, amar lei rabi Zeira, so Rabi Zeira said, מאי שנא
ממיא אגב מיא, mai shna mimaya agav maya, I don't get it,
why is that different than putting, you know, one pot that usually
has hot water in it on top of another pot in order
to keep it warm? So אמר ליה התם אוקומי קמוקים הכא אולודי
קמוליד. amar lei hatam okumi kamokim hacha ulodi kamolid. No, in the
first case you're just keeping it hot. Here you're actually trying to
add heat. You're trying to, so why does it matter? So you
would have thought in our context it's sort of like an issue
of מוסיף הבל, mosif hevel, okay, you know, like that type of
a thing. But it doesn't sound like it. It's not a הטמנה
hatmana case, you know, it's just putting a pot on top of
a pot, especially given the תוספות Tosafot we just read. So therefore
the ראשונים Rishonim generally read that this issue is a concern of
actually about בישול, bishul, not about הטמנה. hatmana. Now תוספות Tosafot says,
okay, so one way to read this difference, a straightforward way is
that in one case the pot you're putting on top is only,
is not going to get to יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo.
It's only going to retain the heat, maybe it'll add but not
significantly. In the second case it will get to יד סולדת בו
yad soledet bo and it will be בישול. bishul. Okay, and then
it's telling us the idea that we knew before, that you can
have a בישול bishul problem even when not directly on the fire,
even when it's from something that has absorbed heat. So you have
a pot that has a lot of absorbed heat, it's been on
the fire, you put it maybe not on the fire, you put
another pot on top of it, is it a problem or not?
Whether it's a problem if the top pot on top is going
to become יד סולדת, yad soledet, not if it won't. But תוספות
Tosafot says, you know, it doesn't sound that way. It doesn't sound
like it's only a problem because the pot on top will get
to be יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. It sounds like it's
a problem as long as you're trying to add heat to the
pot. So תוספות Tosafot tries to say maybe the real difference is,
one was cold water, one was warm water?
Well, yes, and but more to the point that תוספות Tosafot says
that, I mean but again if you read it too much like
that, then you would say you cannot put, you know, something with
cold water near something to warm up and we've learned in previous
פרקים perakim you can warm it up as long as it doesn't
get to יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. So not any type
of adding heat is a problem, we've learned in the, you know,
the previous chapter, as long as it won't get to יד סולדת
בו yad soledet bo you can warm it up. So תוספות Tosafot
wants to say maybe the additional point being made here, and this
is important because we פסקן pasken this way, is that you can't
put it on a place where it might get to יד סולדת
בו yad soledet bo even if you're planning on taking it off
before. hand. And maybe that was the difference. So according to, again,
it’s not really in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but he’s saying that
to try to read it in the context of other סוגיות *sugyos*
and that basically we do say that that if you cannot take
uncooked food or by liquid we treat it even if it was
cooked, if it’s cooled down as if it were uncooked, and you
put it on a place where it in potential could get יד
סולדת בו *Yad Soledet Bo* even if you’re planning on removing it
beforehand. Now again, that’s really nowhere you don’t see that in the
stories. But that’s how תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* wants to read it and
that is important להלכה *lehalacha*. Okay, but the simple sense of the
story is just in one case it’s just not getting, it’s just
staying warm and the other case it’s getting hotter, but as I
said, you can’t read it that that by itself is a problem
because you’re allowed to get stuff hotter if it’s not going to
get to יד סולדת בו *Yad Soledet Bo*.
So then according to that if I, let’s say I have like
a hot plate that won’t get anything to יד סולדת בו *Yad
Soledet Bo*, I could put it on it on שבת Shabbos? *Shabbos*?
Yeah, so the answer to that is yes, if it really won’t
get anything to יד סולדת בו *Yad Soledet Bo*, the answer to
that is yes. Okay. You might still have to worry about like
a חזרה *chazara* issue, but it’s possibly not if it hasn’t even
the potential of getting to יד סולדת בו *Yad Soledet Bo* and
so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
So anyway, so that again, it seems like it should be הטמנה
hatmanah *hatmana* point, but that everybody says it isn’t. So now we
go on to another story which is now that we’re talking about
the people acting incorrectly in the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish
Galuta*, which certainly touches on, you know, still שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* issues
but not exactly our theme, the second story. What’s the second story?
הדר חזי *Hadar chazi*, then he saw him דפרס דסתודא דסתודר אפימי
דכופא *deparas desatuda desatudar apumei dekupa*,
that he spread out some type of a towel or some type
of a cloth on the mouth of a flask, ואנח נטלא עלויה
*ve'anach natla ilavei*,
and he put the cup by it. They would use a cup
to like draw the water from the flask, maybe flask is not
the right word, you know, some type of a water barrel. Okay,
and they would use obviously a cup to draw the water out
of the water barrel. So he put some type of a cloth
on top of the water barrel and he put the cup on
top of the cloth. Now, by the way, I want to just
make a comment about the word נטלא *natla*. נטלא *natla* is a
word in the, is the Aramaic word for the type of cup
used for drawing water, maybe a cup in general, but certainly in
this context. Anyway, so right, so the רשב"א *Rashba* says, maybe others
say this as well, but why do we make the ברכה *bracha*
על נטילת ידים *al netilat yadayim*, right? What do you mean on
the lifting of hands, right? Why didn't you say, right, why you
know, why say על *al* I don’t know, רחיצת ידים *rechitzat yadayim*,
טהרת ידים *taharat yadayim*.
Anyway, so he says that the word נטילה *netila* there refers to
the cup you use. And because you’re, because part of נטילת ידים
*netilat yadayim* requires not just putting it in water, but pouring water
on it with a cup. Okay, so he says it actually means
sort of like the pouring of water with a cup on the
hand or something of that nature. That’s your נטלא *natla*. Anyway, נזגיה
רבא Rava. *nazgei Rava*. So רבא *Rava* yelled at him. So אמר
ליה Amar lei, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira. *amar lei Rabbi Zeira*, so
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said to him: By the way, it’s not
good politics to always be yelling at the servants in the house
of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*. Anyway, maybe after שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*
you want to give a lecture series on, you know, הלכות halachos.
שבת Shabbos *Hilchos Shabbos*, but okay, anyway, so אמר ליה amar lei,
רבי זירא *amar lei Rabbi Zeira*, so רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said
to רבא *Rava*: אמאי *Amai*? Why are you yelling at him? אמר
ליה *Amar lei*: השתא חזי *Hascha chazi*. Oh, watch, now you’ll see.
לסוף חזיה *Lesof chazyei*, so then they waited a while and they
saw him, the servant, דקא מעצר ליה *d'ka ma'atzar lei*, that he
was squeezing out the water of the towel. Because basically the towel
on the top and maybe the cup maybe it made it sink
in or whatever or you were just washing your hands and the
towel was nearby and it got very wet. So you’ll come to
squeeze out the towel. All right, so אמר ליה *amar lei*, so
he knew that it was trouble. אמר ליה *Amar lei*: מאי שנא
מפרונקא *Mai shna mi-parunka*? How is that any different than פרונקא *parunka*,
which apparently is, we learned in another פרק *perek* that that is
something that they allowed you to spread on top of a barrel
on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, a barrel that had liquid in it. So
how is this any different? אמר ליה *Amar lei*: התם hatam, לא
קפיד עילויה הכא hacha, קפיד עילויה *Hatam lo kapid ilavei, hacha kapid
ilavei*. Okay, the difference is that over there he, let me just
I just want to check רש"י Rashi *Rashi*.
Right, so in one case he doesn’t care, in the case of
the פרונקא *parunka*, he’s לא קפיד עילויה *lo kapid ilavei*, he doesn’t
care if it gets wet. So he’s not going to squeeze it
out. This type of a case, what is whatever type of a
cloth that was there, that he knew that if it would get
wet, you would squeeze it out. You don’t want it to be
wet. So the basic point is what?
So but what's the problem of squeezing it out again?
What isn't it...? Yes, you are correct that squeezing out is primarily
two issues: If you want the liquid, it's a type of a
problem of דש *dash*, and if you don't want the liquid, it's
a type of a problem of cleaning. So here, certainly he wasn't
that but you know, so the ראשונים *Rishonim* tried to figure out
what the problem, maybe they're squeezing it out because they're trying to
retrieve liquid, doesn't sound like it here, they're just trying to get
the thing dry. So and that doesn't sound like actually ליבון *libun*
either because it doesn't sound like it's a process of getting it
clean. Although it might be, it might be your אינו מתכוין *eino
mitkaven*, but the result is getting it in water and squeezing it
out does get it clean. So it is a good question how
clear is it that there's a דאורייתא d'oraita *d'oraisa* concern here. And
that is a legitimate point.
But anyway, this point here being the now and this by the
way, this anxiety around squeezing issues comes up in a lot of
places. The whole אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* מנהג *minhag* we mentioned the other time
of not fully immersing yourself in water, one major concern about that
has to do with, you know, squeezing. So anyway, so here you
see that he said, yeah, I was concerned, I knew that if
it was very likely it would get wet, and if it got
wet he wouldn't want it wet, and he'd squeeze it out, and
therefore I said off limits, doesn't mean those types of scenarios are
always problematic, there's cases where it's not a concern but here it
was a concern. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara's continues. ולא בתבן,
Ve-lo be-teven, so another thing you can't use is תבן teven is
straw, presumably also straw will add heat again as it
decomposes. בעא מיניה רב אדא בר מתנא מאביי, Ba'ei minei Rav Ada
bar Matna me-Abaye, רב אדא בר מתנא Rav Ada bar Matna asked
אביי, Abaye, מוכין שטמן בהן. Muchin she-taman ba-hen. So now one of
the things that was also mentioned, it's really not going on the
straw line of the משנה, Mishnah, it's ולא במוכין, ve-lo be-muchin, not
and not with מוכין, muchin, מוכין muchin are little pieces of cloth.
Okay. And the end of the משנה Mishnah by the way says
that by things like the straw and the cloth and so on,
it says only when they're moist. When they're dry it's not a
problem, but when they're moist there is. Again, not exactly clear to
me the chemical מציאות metzius here about why that makes a difference.
But anyway, one of the things you cannot store it in is
moist pieces of cloth, מוכין. muchin. So let's see what the discussion
is. He asked
אביי, Abaye, מוכין שטמן בהן, Muchin she-taman ba-hen, if you went ahead
and you insulated it with מוכין, muchin, so presumably how did you
do that? You're not allowed. So presumably you did it with the
dry מוכין. muchin. You're allowed to do it with the dry pieces
of cloth. So you went ahead and you insulated it with the
dry pieces of cloth, which is
okay. מהו לטלטלן בשבת, Mahuhu letaltelan be-Shabbos, are you allowed to move
the clothy pieces on שבת? Shabbos Normally these cloth pieces are stuff
that you have set aside in your sewing kit and you're going
to use them for patches or who knows what other types of
things. So therefore they're מוקצה. muktzah. They have no legitimate use right
before שבת. Shabbos But what you did is you took a whole
bunch of them and you used it to do הטמנה hatmana. to
put your pot in. Okay. It was dry and it was allowed.
Does that make it not מוקצה? muktzah? Okay. Does that make it
change its identity? Now it's something that's doing a legitimate use on
שבת, Shabbos, it's insulating material for my pot. Does it so can
I now move these things? Now you're going to tell me if
you can't move it, how are you going to get your pot?
So a later משנה Mishnah is going to talk about exactly a
scenario of this sort where you insulate with something that's מוקצה muktzah
and then on שבת Shabbos what you're allowed to do is you
go for the pot and you take it out and it's טלטול
מן הצד, tiltul min ha-tzad, the other stuff is just being moved
incidentally. Remember we discussed that like you're going for one thing in
the you know you're going for I said you know you're going
for your orange and you're moving aside your wallet or something like
that. So that is allowed. That a major discussion of that we're
always getting circling back to מוקצה muktzah is going to come up
as well in this case. But here the question was fine, I
get you can grab the pot and the stuff can move incidentally,
but maybe you should be able to move the מוכין muchin directly.
Maybe you've made them now into non-מוקצה. muktzah. So let's see what
his answer is. אמר
ליה, he said back to him, וכי מפני שאין לו קופה של
תבן עומד ומפקיר קופה של מוכין? Ve-chi mipnei she-ein lo kuppah shel
teven omed u-mafkir kuppah shel muchin? You mean to say that just
because this ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you weren't able to get yourself
a box full of תבן teven straw, now that's it? Now you
are going ahead and giving up on your cloth pieces and now
that what you're going to use them for every ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos is to store your pots in? Of course not. This was
a very ad hoc type of a thing. As soon as שבת
Shabbos is over, you're going to go to the store and buy
תבן teven straw so you can use it for insulating material. This
is going to go back into your sewing kit. So therefore this
has not really changed its identity. Fundamentally this is still sewing pieces
of cloth that are being used to insulate, but it doesn't change
their basic identity and therefore they remain מוקצה. muktzah. Now that's quite
interesting because as I told you, you actually can change things' identity.
I can take a rock which is you don't have a bigger
מוקצה muktzah than that and decide on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos I'm
using it for a doorstop or I'm using it for a paperweight
and it stops being מוקצה. muktzah. But the difference there is is
that there I really have changed its identity. It's not like as
soon as שבת Shabbos is over it's going to go back to
being a rock. I mean, maybe eventually I'll throw it out, you
know, but I don't know, I guess you could imagine a scenario
like that which is which is like I just need the doorstop
for שבת Shabbos because otherwise I'll be carrying my key and there
will be you know etc. You could imagine a case you just
need it for שבת, Shabbos. but even so it's not like you
specifically are designating it for some off-limit purposes afterwards. Here your mind
would be no, obviously I'm not going to use this for this
regularly, afterwards I'm going to go back and put it in my
sewing kit and therefore even though you're currently using it, it does
not make it not מוקצה, muktzah, which is I would say a
very fascinating concept. You would think if anything is not מוקצה, muktzah,
it's something that you have designated for שבת Shabbos. use. But here
we're saying that the identity can go you know is not is
not totally redefined based on that. Yes.
When you say designate for שבת Shabbos. use on Friday, do you
have to say I'm using the straw?
No, no, no. Just in practice, you don't have to make any
verbal statement. I mean if you just had in mind to use
the rock and it was still out in the yard, that's a
different story. You know, you have to take it in and you
know whatever, so there're different degrees but you don't have to make
a verbal statement.
Now on Friday it's the rock, it's מוקצה. muktzah.
Oh, then no.
בין השמשות, Bein ha-shemashos, it's it's מוקצה. muktzah. On Saturday I decide
it's a paperweight? No, no. So you have to have it in
mind.
Yes, having it in mind might not even be enough if it's
something like, you know, right, exactly what's needed to designate? Is it
verbal, in mind, and on what stages? The more something, you know,
is out of your realm, the more like, you know, you might
need to do something practical to make it non-מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, so
we haven't really fully explored. Sure, sure.
Okay, yeah. Is that what the חרדי Charedi
do when they throw rocks
at cars? Really?
They pre-designate rocks.
All right, moving on. After throwing rocks at cars.
All right, so that's his answer. His answer is it remains מוקצה.
muktzeh. לימא מסייע ליה, Lima masayei lei, let me try to bring
support to it, this. תומנין בגיזי צמר, Tomnin begizei tzemmer,
you can insulate with like shearings of wool. ובציפי צמר, Uvetzipei tzemmer,
ציפי צמר tzipei tzemmer is also like רש״י Rashi says it's also
shearings of wool after you have done some of the combing, you
haven't yet made it into actual wool string. ובלשונות של ארגמן, Uvilshonot
shel argaman, strips of, yeah, you know, what do
they call it, crimson,
ובמוכין uvimochin or and in little pieces of cloth. Now, all these
types of things are things that on שבת Shabbos, you would normally
these are things that you're going to use in sewing, right? You're
going to turn it into thread, you're going to use your cloth,
you're going to use all these things. But you've used it to
insulate. Okay. ואין מטלטלין אותן. Ve'ein metalpelin otan. But it
says you can't move them, they're מוקצה. muktzeh. Oh, so it's explicit!
Here you have your case of the pieces of cloth and it
says it's מוקצה. muktzeh. So the גמרא Gemara... says no. אי משום
הא לא איריא. Ei mishum ha lo irya. If that was your
only proof, that wouldn't have proven it. Why? הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar.
I would have said that this is how to read it. אם
לא טמן בהן אין מטלטלין אותן. Im lo taman bahen ein metalpelin
otan. It's telling me two separate הלכות. One, you can use it
for הטמנה. hatmana B, under normal circumstances they're מוקצה. muktzeh. But it
wouldn't tell me that if you actually used it for הטמנה hatmana
they remain מוקצה, muktzeh, which was my question. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי הכי מאי למימרא, ei hachi mai lemeymra, so what should
be the חידוש? chiddush? Of course we know these things are מוקצה.
muktzeh. No, מהו דתימא חזי למזגא עלייהו, mahu d'teima chazi lemizga aleihu,
I might think that some of these things maybe you want to
lie on, like these pieces of cloth you want to use them
like, I don't know, as a little bit of a cushion. קמ"ל
Kamashma lan that no, that these are sewing cloths, these are not
the type of normal use and they'd be מוקצה. muktzeh. So anyway,
you can't prove it from the ברייתא, Baraisa, but in the end
the גמרא's Gemara discussion is that yes, even after you used them,
they remain מוקצה muktzeh because that has not really changed their identity.
Okay? So now the גמרא...
Gemara Let's say you actually specifically did say, okay, I'm going to
use it...
Okay, if you really are changing it and every שבת Shabbos. you're
going to use it for insulating, it's a different story. Now the
גמרא Gemara goes on with little pieces of cloth to do another
issue that we dealt with yesterday, again a very relevant issue about
making כלים. keilim. Let's take a look. רב חסדא שרא לאדורי אודרא
לבי סדיא בשבתא. Rav Chisda shara l'adurei udra le-ve sadya beshabata. Rav
Chisda allowed people to put back like the cloth, the filler, inside
of pillows on שבת. Shabbos, So you have a pillow that some
of the stuffing is coming out, he says fine, put the stuffing
back. Okay, the only relevance here is that we're talking about like
pieces of cloth or something. Okay. איתיביה רב חנן בר חסדא לרב
חסדא. Eitivei Rav Chanan bar Chisda l'Rav Chisda. So presumably רב חסדא's
Rav Chisda's son, רב חנן, Rav Chanan, asked his father. So he
said מתיר בית הצואר בשבת אבל לא פותחין. matir beit hatzavar beShabbos
aval lo potchin. That we say that you can undo this sort
of hole of the neck hole of the garment, but you cannot
open it from the beginning, which means what? That if you basically
would bring your garment to a dry cleaner, they might tie a
certain, you know, make a stitch or whatever to keep it closed
for some type of the processing purpose. Of other thing that my
dry cleaner always does is puts a little tag on stuff. So
that is something that's made just temporarily during the processing and is
made to take off. So that type of thing you can take
off on שבת. Shabbat. It's not like you're making the garment, even
if what they did was they sewed up a hole
that should have been there because that was just for temporary and
then they were going to remove it. But if when you first
bought the garment, like when you buy some suits, right, the pockets
are sewn shut, right, you open up that initial hole to and
that's the making of the
garment, it had never been complete the garment, then that you can't
do. So this is making of a כלי keli on שבת. Shabbat
Okay, so that's the beginning. And then it says ואין נותנין את
המוכין, ve'ein notnin et hamochin, and you cannot put the מוכין, mochin,
there's the connection, right, these pieces of cloth, לא לתוך הכר
ולא לתוך הכסת, lo letoch hakar velo letoch hakeset, not into the
cushion and not into the, you know, and not into the pillow
ביום טוב ואין
צריך לומר בשבת. beYom Tov ve'ein tzarich lomar beShabbos.
You can't do it on יום טוב Yom Tov and you certainly
can't do it on שבת, Shabbat. right? So no difference, it's not
אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. Okay. So לא קשיא, lo kashya,
so you see you're not allowed to do it. So what do
you say to that? That's not difficult. הא בחדתי הא בעתיקי. Ha
bachadti ha ba'atiki.
It depends if it's old or new. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, hold on a minute, אין נותנין את המוכין לא לתוך הכר
ולא לתוך הכסת ביום טוב ואין צריך לומר בשבת, ein notnin et
hamochin lo letoch hakar velo letoch hakeset beYom Tov ve'ein tzarich lomar
beShabbos, you can't put the stuffing in on יום טוב Yom Tov
or on שבת. Shabbat, נשרו מחזירין אותן בשבת, Nashru machzirin otan beShabbos,
if it fell out,
you can put it back on שבת, Shabbat.
ואין צריך לומר ביום טוב, ve'ein tzarich lomar beYom Tov, and you
certainly can do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, now, so
why is it old? So right, because it seems like if it's
new, then you actually are making a pillow. If it's old, right,
then you're not... it's already made and you're just putting it back
and therefore you're not doing any big deal. Now, of course, it's
not right, so of course the question becomes by a lot of
these things which is like, you know. know, but if something breaks
and you fix it, it is מכה בפטיש. Makeh b'patish. So what
stage do you consider something broken, or what stage like, you know,
if you know, I mean, there are different degrees in which stuffing
is falling out. You know, there could be type of a of
a thing where, you know, you have one of these like Styrofoam
fillers and you have like a, you know, a cloth what, you
know, like a type of a cover around it. So the Styrofoam
filler came out. Fine, you put the cover back in, right? You
have something else where really it's like falling apart and you're really
like, you know, reconstituting it in some way and it really is
considered to be like broken. So a major question when these are
hard to always define the line is exactly this. It's like: A,
how much regularly it is that it moves from one stage to
the other; B, how much it's like a tight type of a
fit, things we discussed before; how much it requires maybe a certain
amount of expertise. I'll give you an example that happens that happens
that's a pretty common one, which is: your temple of your glasses
falls off, right? So to fix it, you have to screw, okay?
So that you can't do on שבת. Shabbat, Okay, but also though,
that's something that if it happens, like some people, it's always happening
every other day. So it's not like, right, for some people it's
like it was it's unusual, and that might make it different. Anyway,
what I do is I put a toothpick in or some type
of a thing in the hole, depends if it actually works. Sometimes
you go around all of שבת Shabbat. holding it like this. Anyway,
but there are these types of issues if things break, right, what's
considered to be a making it new and what's considered to be
just like restoring it. And as I said, a large of it
might have to do with tightness, how tight is the thing fitting,
and how regularly does it happen and so on. There's actually an
interesting question: does quantity matter?
Like if half your pillow fell out?
Yeah, but still if it's like it's always happening and it's not
a big deal and you just put it right back in, then
no. I mean, there's an interesting question that some פוסקים poskim ask
about: let's say you bought an inflatable bed or an inflatable cushion,
and you blow it up for the first time on שבת. Shabbat,
Right, so there it was never a cushion. But, so but is
that חדתי chadati or no? There it's always made for filling and
unfilling and releasing or whatever. So even if it was never that
way, it's not really like making a כלי. kli. There was a
discussion about if your watch stops, can you wind your watch? So
is it considered to be not a watch, not a working watch?
How much, you know, but that's a regular type of thing you
do. So anyway, there's a lot of literature on and a lot
of different opinions on at what stage is it considered to be
just restoring and at what stage is it considered to be making.
Yes. Does a
puzzle fall into this category also? Puzzle could be, yeah. I mean,
I know that a puzzle is a big activity on שבת, Shabbat
but I, you know, to me it seems like it's certainly a
some form of כותב kotev in the sense, I mean not letters,
but you're making a picture. And it depends, you know, maybe you'll
argue that you know as soon as you do it you take
it apart, but a lot of people they do it, they keep
it that way, they frame it, whatever. So a puzzle, but whether
puzzle's like a מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish of a כלי, kli, maybe
if you finish it and you make like a picture, and it's
a picture you're going to hang, but I think there's issues before
you get to מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish with a puzzle. Okay, anyway,
so let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. נשים מחזירין.
Nashim machzirin. עמוד א'. Amud aleph. סוף שבת. Sof Shabbat. שאינו מן
המנוי. She'eino min hamenuy. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, הפותח בית הצואר בשבת. Hapoteach beit hatzavar b'Shabbat. Now that
we mentioned you can't open, you know, the neck hole on a
new garment. So again for our example, I would say it would
be like the pockets of like a suit, of a jacket. Anyway,
if you do it,
חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. It's a מלאכה דאורייתא. melacha d'Oraita. You've actually
מכה בפטיש. makeh b'patish. You've made a garment on שבת. Shabbat, So
מתיב ליה רב כהנא, Metiv lei Rav Kahana, so רב כהנא Rav
Kahana asked on this, מ"ח עמוד ב', Mem-chet amud bet, מה בין
זו למגופת חבית? Mah bein zu l'megupat chavit? How is this different
than the the seal of a barrel? Now, what's the story of
a seal of a barrel? So רש"י Rashi refers to a גמרא
Gemara that says if you have your barrel sealed on שבת, Shabbat.
you are allowed to chop off the top of the barrel in
order to get to the wine. But as we'll see in a
minute, the גמרא's Gemara answer is going to say it has to
do with the the top of the barrel being removable. But so
רש"י's Rashi. answer that you're chopping off the whole top of the
barrel isn't related to the removable part. You're not dealing with the
cover, you're actually dealing you're actually chopping the barrel itself according to
רש"י. Rashi. So תוספות Tosafot says no. תוספות's Tosafot explanation is much
clearer, also because it's, you know, conceptually related. He's saying that what
we're talking about is that you're allowed to make a hole in
the in the in the top of the barrel in order to
basically, you know, with an as like a spigot to the hole
in order to draw out the wine. So you've got a barrel
top, you know, a barrel of wine, you've got the top, you
made a hole in it, you're not chopping anything off, you made
a hole in it, and you're getting out the wine. So how
is it different? I can't make a hole in my garment because
it's making it usable, but I can make a hole in my
barrel top to make it usable, right? And this obviously you see
gets into the question of opening packages, right? Can I make a
can I open my, you know, can I open my soda bottle,
can I open my, you know, you know, my tuna fish can?
So you're making a hole in the barrel top. It's like making
a hole in the garment. Why is it different?
It's not the seal according to רש"י.
Rashi. Right, you're not removing the seal. No, no, no, right, right,
exactly. You're actually doing something new, you're not just removing a seal.
That would be obvious. But look, you know, I don't... I don't
know how much they still sell—oh, they do—these—I always buy the plastic
milk, but they sell more like the paper rectangular milk cartons where
when you open it, you actually make like a spout, right? So,
you know, so you do these types of things. So is that
allowed on—or in Israel certainly, you got your plastic bag, you make
a hole, right? So is that making a vessel? So a lot
of those scenarios, by the way, are disposable. And disposable, you know,
makes—changes the story because that could—if you're going to throw it out
right away, how much can you really call it a vessel? רב
משה Rav Moshe distinguishes between them even if you're going to use
it for the length of the time that you're getting the stuff
out, once all the stuff is out, if you throw it away,
although people do distinguish between the two cases, Michael said, are you
just opening it and throwing it away immediately or do you keep
on using it till you get the stuff out? But if, you
know, but there are some cases where you'll use it even after
you get the stuff out, some type of like glass jars or
whatever, afterwards you wash it out and you use it. So that's
obviously makes it much—so one, a lot of our scenarios are disposable,
which makes it a lot better. But this is the—one of the
major discussions about making—about opening, you know, vessels on שבת. Shabbat? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers to this, okay? So his
question is: How come you can't open a, you know, the garment,
but you can make a hole in the barrel top? So אמר
ליה רבא זה חיבור וזה אינו חיבור. Amar lei Rava zeh chibur
v'zeh eino chibur. One is connected, the other isn't connected. Which means
what? That, you know, the—the—the garment is all sewn together, whereas the
barrel top is made, you know, the—the cover was never really fully,
you know, made together. Now, of course, the point is, you know,
in both cases, like, you know, you put a cover on, you
sewed it together. What exactly is the difference? So let's look at
רש"י. Rashi רש"י Rashi, says
מגופה, Megupa, third wide line of רש"י, Rashi אינו מן החבית עצמה.
eino min ha'chavis atzmah. ואף על פי שדבוקה בה, Ve'af al pi
she'devuka bah, even though—so the cover starts independent of the barrel, even
though now you're sealing it onto it, so
חשיב חיבור—I'm chashiv chibur sorry, אינו חשיב חיבור, eino chashiv chibur, שהרי
לינטל עומדת. she'harei lintol omedes. It was separate, it was put on,
and it was made for the purpose of removing, or תוספות Tosafot
would say for the purpose of making a hole in it, but
it never really was like a permanent part of it. אבל הבגד
כשנארג כולו חיבור. Aval ha'beged k'shenearag kulo chibur. רש"י says the garment
when it was sewed, it was all sort of like sewed as
a unit. Presumably even if you sewed together this opening, right, that
was still somehow seen as like the initial garment, it wasn't bringing
something in out—from the outside. Okay. So this becomes the difference that—I
mean, the way I would reframe it is that in one case
you're actually like making the garment, you're making the בגד, beged, here
you're not making the barrel, you're making a hole in a cover,
and a hole in a cover isn't like making a vessel. So
though the barrel becomes usable because you can get the stuff out
of the cover, right, the hole isn't in the barrel. If you
make the hole in the barrel, you have a problem, but the
hole's in the cover, and the cover isn't the vessel itself. Okay.
According to this, of course, any holes in packages where it is
part of the whole unit could be a problem, right? So this
is only half of the conversation, and as I said, disposable is
another—is an important factor. Yes.
Yeah, application to opening packages on שבת, Shabbat. whether or not they
were delivered on שבת Shabbat or not.
What do you mean?
Like, so I don't want to get—that also gets to חוץ לתחום
chutz l'techum issue. Where is it coming from? No, they came before.
They came before and I forgot to open it. And it's my
Tums for the day.
So anyway, so as I said, so certainly there's a whole issue
about opening something up דרך קלקול derech kilkul and totally destroying the
packaging. Okay. Generally, you know, if you want—here's a—look, there's another discussion
about it later which—which is also the sort of the comparable discussion,
but I will tell you a short answer is: If you're destroying
the packaging in the process, it's not a problem. Okay. So you
forgot to open your package of some—of like napkins for שבת, Shabbat.
right? So if you just totally like rip the plastic to shreds,
as it were, then—that's fine. Okay. So if you got to—if you
got to rip your box open into pieces, not so that you
can reuse it as a good box, okay, you know, then certainly
that would be okay if it came before שבת. All right. Even
if it's destruction for a purpose? Well, it's destruction to get—not to
do something with the box, to make the box usable, but to
get what's inside. So you're really completely not interested in the box.
So does it see back to the cans or do you not
want to do that?
No, no.
I'm sorry, but for now we will say—the point is, by the
way, though, it is relevant for like the bottle top conversation because
the bottle top is separate from the bottle. And I believe in
like tuna fish cans, no, they have to make it—do they make
it as one unit or is—is the top a separate unit and
they fuse it on?
Top is a separate unit and they seal it on. Ah, so
same way for aluminum beverage cans.
Okay. So anyway, so there's some relevance to those types of cases,
okay, when you're actually making the—the
change in the cover, not in the thing itself. All right. And
how much do you consider the cover like a separate כלי? keli?
So all sorts of deals with whether it is disposable. Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Okay. רמי ליה רבי
ירמיה לרבי זירא, Rami lei Rabbi Yirmiyah l'Rabbi Zeira, so רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah challenged רבי זירא. תנן שלשה קובסין ושלשלת של מפתחות, Tenan:
shlosha kuvsin v'shalsheles shel maftechos,
you have a—you have a like a bunch of garments that were
laundered and what they would do is they would sew a thread
to combine your— one person's garments all together as they were doing
the laundry and then שלשול Shalshul means this type of a bunch,
a bunch of כובסין kobasin of people's garments. שלשול Shalshul means this...
in a person's garments all together as
they were doing the laundry and then, it's a שללים, shalalim, it's
this type of a bunch, a bunch of laundry, כובסין kobasin of
people's garments. שללים Shalalim means this... I don't know. Anyway, that's what
it means in this context. So they would, they would string together,
so, you know, these garments but obviously it was only for while
they were laundering them and then they would separate. שלשלת של מפתחות
Shalshelet shel maftechot is a keychain, okay, או הבגד שתפור בכלאים o
habeged she'tafur be'kilayim
or let's say you have a wool garment and a linen garment
and for some reason, you know, you had to carry them together,
so you, you, you sewed the two of them together with a
string or you made a... so obviously, or I think Rashi might
even say the string makes it כלאים. kilayim. What does Rashi say?
One minute. ובין שתי חטיות. uvein shtei chitiyot. No, I'm sorry, I
said it the way Rashi said it. Anyway, so all those scenarios
it's only there temporarily. The case of the laundry you're going to
cut the string as soon as the laundry is done, the case
of the keys, well, apparently they did not have a permanent keychain,
they had sometimes you would bunch them together and then undo them,
and the case of the כלאים kilayim certainly you're not, you're going
to cut it before it's worn because you're not allowed to keep
the stuff sewn together. So what's the הלכה halacha of all these
types of temporary connections? So it says חיבור לטומאה עד שיתחיל להתיר.
chibur l'tumah ad she'yatchil l'hatir.
They're considered to be connected for טומאה tumah purposes until you begin
to undo the string, even though the string is now made for
undoing and it's going to be undone. So meaning the connection for
טומאה tumah is if you touch one garment the other garments become
טמא. tamei. Normally, right, one garment cannot make another טמא, tamei, but
if they're seen as one big unit, then when it's like touching
a part, right, the sleeve of a garment, the whole garment is
טמא. tamei. So if I have five garments sewn together, it's seen
as one unit, you touch one, the others become טמא. tamei. Even
though they're only connected by this string temporarily. Okay, so that's one
thing, very nice. So what's the challenge? Because how does this sit
with the next teaching? So it says like this, אלמא, alma, we
see from this, שלא בשעת מלאכה נמי חיבור, shelo b'sha'at melacha nami
chibur, that even though you're not, you're done doing the laundry, it
remains considered connected until you actually begin to undo it. It says
עד שיתחיל להתיר. ad she'yatchil l'hatir. Okay, so when you're not actually
doing the מלאכה, melacha, it still is considered connected, even though you're
done for the purpose that you sewed it together. ורמינהו, u'reminhu, I'll
ask you on that: מקל שעשאו יד לקורדום, makel she'asao yad l'kardom,
let's say you have a hatchet head and it doesn't have the
handle. So what you did was you picked up a stick that
you found in the woods, you picked up some stick and you
used it for the handle and that's totally temporary, temporary, it's not,
it's not going to be your permanent solution, it was a, it
was a like, you know, an ad hoc solution. So חיבור לטומאה,
chibur l'tumah, it's considered one unit for טומאה, tumah, if you touch
the stick, it like the whole thing becomes טמא. tamei. It's one
unit, the stick by itself wouldn't be טמא tamei anyway, but now
it's a new vessel. בשעת מלאכה, bish'at melacha, while it's still the
time that you're in the, that you're using the hatchet. Okay, so
if you're still in the middle of using it, then it's still
considered one unit. בשעת מלאכה אין, bish'at melacha in, here's the challenge,
only when it's being used. שלא בשעת מלאכה לא, shelo b'sha'at melacha
lo, when you're done, I'm done for the day, tomorrow I'm going
to go out tonight and go to the store and get myself
a real handle, right? So then it stops being considered connected. This
is what I did for the day, but when you're done with
it, it's no longer considered one unit. So how is that different?
How is this case different than the sewn together garments? You got
the question? Okay, really nothing to do exactly with our משנה, mishna,
but now we're talking about pieces of garments and all these types
of things. Okay, and sewing together things as well because of making
vessels and so on. So אמר ליה, he said to him, התם,
there, שלא בשעת מלאכה, shelo b'sha'at melacha, אדם עשוי לזורקו לבין העצים.
adam asuy l'zorko l'vein ha'etzim. There, as soon as you are done
with it, what are you going to do? You're going to take
it and throw it into your woodpile. Okay, so as soon as
you're done using it for the day, in your mind already it's
no longer part of that hatchet, it's going into the woodpile. הכא,
here, שלא בשעת מלאכה, shelo b'sha'at melacha, even when you're done laundering
these garments, נמי ניחא ליה, nami nicha lei, you want the string
to be on it. Why do you want the string to be
on it? דאי מיתנפו, d'ei mitnapu, because if for some reason they
still get, if something gets soiled again, הדר מחבר להו, hadar mechaber
lehu, so you'll go ahead and you'll clean it again. So and
you're glad because it's still connected. So although I'm done with it
immediately, I still want it to be on until I'm ready to
take it off. And therefore it's still considered connected as opposed to
the hatchet case where even if you haven't gotten around to taking
it off, you're done with it. Alright, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara says is the conceptual difference. Now I'm confused too because if
it was a good enough solution for you to use this as
the handle for the day, why don't you say you want it
on there until you actually go to the store and replace it?
I don't know. So we must be assuming that you've got a
ready replacement, I really don't know, okay? But at least that's the
conceptual difference the גמרא Gemara makes, even if you're not, you know,
having the immediate use of it, you still want it on there.
Yes?
And what would you be doing with an axe on שבת?
No, it's not שבת. These are all, we're circling back to שבת
cases and related cases, but this is just a question for טומאה,
tumah, is it one unit or not for טומאה tumah purposes?
Okay, then you used that to talk about...
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. בסורא
מתנו להא שמעתא משמיה דרב חסדא,
be'Sura matnu l'ha
shma'ta mishmeih d'Rev Chisda,
in סורא Sura they teach the following discussion, not the previous the
following discussion, in the name of רב חסדא. Rev Chisda. בפומבדיתא מתנו
משמיה דרב כהנא, be'Pumbedita matnu mishmeih d'Rev Kahana, in פומבדיתא Pumbedita they
tell it in the name of רב כהנא. Rev Kahana. ואמרי לה
משמיה דרבא, ve'amri lah mishmeih d'Rava, some say in the name of
רבא. מאן תנא הא מילתא דאמרי רבנן כל המחובר לו הרי הוא
כמהו? Man tanna ha milta d'amri Rabbanan kol ha'mechubar lo harei hu
kamoho?
Who is the תנא Tanna that says that anything that is connected
becomes one unit, meaning we just said whether it's the handle to
the hatchet or whether it's the pieces of whether it's the clothing
that's sewn together it's one unit for טומאה. tumah. Okay, who is
the person that says that because look let's face it even if
you had sewn together ten different shirts it's not one shirt it's
still ten shirts sewn together and nevertheless for טומאה tumah purposes we're
treating it as one shirt and when one part becomes טמא tamei
others become טמא. tamei. Who is the one that says that? So
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אמר רבי מאיר היא. Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav Amar Rabbi Meir hi. It's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דתנן
detnan we taught in the משנה. mishnah. בית הפך ובית הטבלין ובית
הנר שבכירה. Beit hapach uveit hatavlin uveit haner shebakira. You have your
oven and apparently attached to your oven you've got little like holders
for oil and for spices and for a candle so these are
all like little sort of you know like you have these cup
holders or whatever that you attach to tables so they had that
type of stuff that attached to an oven. Okay so is it
considered to be one unit with the oven or not? שבכירה מיטמאים
במגע ואין מיטמאים באויר דברי רבי מאיר. shebakira mitam'in bemaga ve'ein mitam'in
be'avir divrei Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if you
touch one of those or you touch the oven everything else becomes
טמא. tamei. It's one unit. But if you have something because this
is a pottery and pottery becomes טמא tamei by something being suspended
in the air so if it's suspended in the air and actually
touched the bottom everything becomes טמא. tamei. But if it's only suspended
in the air and hasn't touched the bottom then they're not one
unit and only the oven becomes טמא tamei if the טמא tamei
thing was in the air of the oven and the other things
do not. So that's an interesting split. We'll see about that. That's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי שמעון מטהר. Rabbi Shimon metaher.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says they're always considered separate. So at least
you see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir considers things that really are
separate units he's willing to consider them one when they're physically connected.
Okay but he still splits it so what's the logic of that
split? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא לרבי שמעון Bishlama
le'Rabbi Shimon I get רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon קסבר לאו ככירה דמו
kasavar lav kekira damu fine they're not one unit with the כירה.
kira. אלא רבי מאיר Ela Rabbi Meir but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
אי ככירה דמו ei kekira damu if these things are like the
כירה kira אפילו באויר נמי ליטמו. afilu be'avir nami litemu. If they're
one unit with the כירה kira then let them become then when
the oven becomes טמא tamei because of the rodent suspended in its
air let them become טמא. tamei. אי לאו ככירה דמו ei lav
kekira damu and if it's not like the oven
אפילו במגע נמי לא ליטמו. afilu bemaga nami lo litemu. Then even
if the oven becomes טמא tamei because something fell in the air
and hit the ground let them not become טמא. tamei. So what's
the difference? Right make up your mind is it one unit or
not one unit? What's this distinction between the air space and actually
touching it? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לעולם לאו ככירה
דמו Le'olam lav kekira damu really it's not like the oven ורבנן
הוא דגזרו בהו Verabbanan hu degazru behu and it's the Rabbis that
said we'll treat it as one unit with the oven. אי גזרו
בהו ei gazru behu so the גמרא Gemara says אפילו באויר נמי
ליטמו. afilu be'avir nami litemu. So if that's true so fine it's
דרבנן derabbanan what do I care? Still make it טמא tamei when
it's in the air space of the oven. So the גמרא Gemara
says
no: עבדו בה רבנן היכירא כי היכי דלא ליתו למשרף עליה תרומה
וקדשים. Avdu bah Rabbanan heichira ki heichi d'lo leitu l'misraf alei terumah
ve'kodashim. Sometimes we see it's very interesting and תוספות Tosafot points this
out that sometimes in laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve'taharah we want
to make it so clear how strict we are about the דרבנן
derabbanan that we'll say you even are going to burn תרומה terumah
even if it's only a דרבנן derabbanan טומאה. tumah. And sometimes we
say we don't want you to burn תרומה terumah if תרומה terumah
touched this because it's only דרבנן derabbanan and therefore we have to
make the laws a little bit funny so that you remember that
this is only דרבנן. derabbanan. So since it's only דרבנן derabbanan we
don't want if תרומה terumah touched one of these side you know
sort of whatever
receptacles that biblically they're not טמא tamei so if תרומה terumah touches
it we don't want you to burn תרומה. terumah. How do we
make you remember that it's only דרבנן? derabbanan? We create this funny
law that it's only a problem if the טומאה tumah goes falls
in the oven and touches it but if it's suspended no and
that way you'll remember oh yeah it's one of those crazy דרבנן
derabbanan things which doesn't follow any normal laws because you're so well-versed
in טומאה וטהרה tumah ve'taharah you'll remember that. So anyway so the
basic so the point being that all the previous discussion that said
it's one unit the גמרא Gemara says it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't hold biblically it's one unit right
even the גמרא says who says it's one unit? Ah רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir himself only said it was
דרבנן derabbanan and made this split type of a law and that
makes sense. Why would you consider ten garments even if they're sewn
together to be one garment? They're not one garment they're ten garments
sewn together. So even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only says it's דרבנן.
derabbanan. Now תוספות Tosafot says wait one minute why therefore by the
oven did we make some split about the laws? We didn't hear
about a split about the laws before about the garments so we're
about to see that yes even the garments have a split and
that's coming up right now let's take a look what it
is. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan so we taught in a ברייתא. baraita.
מספורת של פרקים Misporet shel perakim if you have scissors that are
like a that are different components you have to assemble the scissors.
All scissors? What? All scissors. Yeah but normally we don't assemble them
on a regular basis. This is the type of thing that the
normal person would take apart and put together.
Okay so they say they're kind of like slotted you know at
the center
so you can take them apart.
Okay so that would be something like
that. רהיטני rehatni or like a carpenter's
plane, you would put a piece of metal in a wood sort
of handle and you would use it to flatten, to finish the
wood.
I saw scissors pictures, just like modern ones.
Yeah, I saw Shandal's pictures, it's very nice pictures. Anyway, so that
thing as well you would disassemble it and reassemble it, right? Sort
of the metal part and the wooden handle. Okay. So, what's the
story there? חבור לטומאה ואין חבור להזאה. Chibbur l'tumah v'ein chibbur l'haza'ah.
They're considered to be one unit when it becomes to becoming טמא.
tamei. If טומאה tumah touches one of them, one blade of the
scissors or one part of the plane, it's all טמא. tamei. But
when you have to sprinkle ashes of a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
on it, if it was in the house of a dead body,
then it's not enough to sprinkle ashes on one part of the
components. The ashes have to touch both parts. It doesn't have to
touch like the entire surface of an object. If my jacket became
טמא tamei in an אוהל המת, ohel hamais, right? You sprinkle ashes
on a part of the jacket. It doesn't have to cover the
entire surface. But if they're considered as two objects, ashes have to
touch both parts of it, or the ash water, not the ashes,
the water with the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah has
to touch both parts of it. So they're considered one unit for
being strict, for טומאה, tumah, but when you're being lenient, they're considered
two units and you have to get the waters of the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah on both of them. So it's again, so the
point is here, it's this as well is the split ruling. By
the oven we said the split ruling was airspace versus touching. Here
the split ruling is it's only considered one unit דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So
therefore, how do we make the split ruling? Well for טומאה tumah
it'll be one unit, but for sprinkling the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
that'll actually be separate. And actually
that's not even a דרבנן d'rabbanan split because since it's all דרבנן,
d'rabbanan, there's no way we could say it works by hitting one
component. Since biblically they're separate units, right? If you're coming to be
מטהר m'taher it, you have to get ashes on both. Okay, so
therefore, but what we can do is we can דרבנן d'rabbanan be
strict and say when it's combined, טומאה tumah for part is טומאה
tumah for all. So it says, this is why you'll remember it's
דרבנן d'rabbanan as opposed, why didn't we say that by the oven?
Because the oven is pottery. The oven you can never be מטהר
m'taher with ashes of פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So therefore you needed
that type of a split of airspace touching. This you can be
מטהר, m'taher, so that allows us for that split and that you
will remember it. Now I should also say the תוספות points out
because he's trying to reconcile various things, that there's a conceptual difference
between these cases. The garments and the receptacles function independently. And when
you combine them, that's a question, are they one unit or not
one unit? This logically is very different. These component parts don't function
separately and they only function together. So logically here you'd be much
more inclined to think that this is one unit even biblically. So
it's quite interesting the way the גמרא is sort of comparing it.
Let's keep on going. It says like this: So, חבור לטומאה, Chibbur
l'tumah, they're one unit for טומאה, tumah, if something touches it becomes
טמא. tamei. ואין חבור להזאה, V'ein chibbur l'haza'ah, not for sprinkling of
the ashes, there you have to do on both component parts. So
the גמרא says: ממה נפשך. mamma nafshach. Make up your mind. אי
חבור הוא, ei chibbur hu, if it's considered connected, אפילו הזאה נמי,
afilu haza'ah nami, it should work for the ashes, assuming it's a
biblically considered connected. אי לאו חבור הוא, ei lav chibbur hu, if
it's not considered biblically one unit, אפילו טומאה נמי לא, afilu tumah
nami lo, so it shouldn't be a problem for טומאה. tumah. So
now we're going to go again to a
דאורייתא דרבנן d'rabbanan split. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דבר תורה, devar Torah,
biblically speaking, בשעת מלאכה חבור. bish'at melacha chibbur. It is one unit
when you're actually using them together. When you're actually using the scissors,
you're using the plane, then obviously it's functioning as one unit, it's
one unit, that's even biblical. בין לטומאה ובין להזאה. Bein l'tumah uvein
l'haza'ah. And biblically, of course, it would be one unit whether it's
for טומאה tumah purposes or for making it pure. ושלא בשעת מלאכה,
v'shelo bish'at melacha, when you're, now apparently this would be the type
of thing that as soon as you're done with it, you take
it apart and you put it away. Okay, so when it's working
together and you're using it, it's one unit biblically. When you're done
with it, then you would deconstruct it, disassemble it, then אינו חבור
לא לטומאה ולא להזאה. eino chibbur lo l'tumah v'lo l'haza'ah. It's not
considered connected. So therefore, that's the biblical story. It all matters whether
it's the time of using it or not. Let's just finish this
up, top of
מ"ט ע"א. mem tet amud aleph. וגזרו רבנן על טומאה שלא בשעת
מלאכה משום טומאה שבשעת מלאכה. V'gazru Rabbanan al tumah shelo bish'at melacha
mishum tumah shebish'at melacha. But what the Rabbis said is, look, we
have to treat it as, we're going to treat it rabbinically as
one unit even when you are not in the process of using
it. Okay, so even though you're done using your plane or your
scissors, we're still going to rabbinically treat it as one unit. All
right. ועל הזאה שבשעת מלאכה משום הזאה שלא בשעת מלאכה. V'al haza'ah
shebish'at melacha mishum haza'ah shelo bish'at melacha. And in the reverse, we're
not going to, when you are sprinkling the ashes of the פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, we're going to rabbinically be strict and say even
if it's during the time where you're still planning on using it,
we're still going to treat them as separate units. So the end
result will be that for טומאה tumah it'll always be one unit
and for הזאה haza'ah it'll always be two units. Let me sort
of simplify the point. The point is like this: biblically it's all
the same, but rabbinically, whether it's time of being used or not
the time of being used, but rabbinically we're going to be strict.
We're not going to make a distinction whether it's being used or
not being used, we're going to be strict. So what does being
strict mean? Being strict means it's easier to become טמא, tamei, it's
harder to become טהור. tahor. So therefore, since rabbinically we're going to
be strict, we're going to say it'll always become טמא, tamei, meaning
whether it's שעת מלאכה shat melacha or not שעת מלאכה, shat melacha,
it's always seen as one unit, it always becomes טמא, tamei, and
it will be harder, we will be מחמיר machmir for becoming טהור.
tahor. So when it comes to the being טהור, tahor, it'll always
be two units, whether the time of using it or not the
time of using it. And with that we end this discussion which
seems like a complete digression, but since we were talking about sewing
together the neck openings of garments, we talked about sewing together various
types of garments, okay? Tomorrow we will return to discussing הטמנה and
שבת.